Okay. And it is recording.
>> Um it says a non number.
>> Good afternoon everybody. Uh just wanted
to check in with everybody. Um we are
just waiting for people to finish
joining. Um there has been a large
number of attendees for this particular
uh this particular group and so we're
just trying to make sure that people are
able to get in and so we will start in a
few minutes. So just please bear with us
for a little bit. Thank you.
Hey, good uh good afternoon everybody.
Um we have had as I mentioned earlier
for those who were on when we opened the
meeting, we've had quite a few people
who are joining. We still have some
people who are joining right now. uh and
so we're letting them on in, but we do
have since we have so many folks and we
want to um we want to make sure that
we're valuing people's time, we're going
to go ahead and get started. Um so
again, my name Dominic Zerlo. I'm the
director for the New Mexico Department
of Health Center for Medical Cannabis
and Psilocybin. And we have a few of our
team members who are here today. Um and
I'm going to go ahead and uh ask them to
introduce themselves. Um, Jorge, why
don't you go next?
>> Hello. Good afternoon, everyone. I am
Jorge Gonzalez, the medical psilocyment
program manager.
>> Thank you, Jorge. Uh, Brenda,
>> I am Brenda Burgard and I am chairing
this meeting for education and training
for psilocybin.
>> Thank you, Brenda. I actually had met
our uh staff member, Brenda Martinez,
but that's a great thing and I'm glad
you introduced yourself. Um, that'll
save me from doing it here in a minute,
but go ahead. Uh, Brenda Martinez.
>> Absolutely. Good morning. Good
afternoon, everyone. Brenda Martinez.
I'm the deputy director here at the
center.
>> And we have uh Dr. Robert Truckner.
>> Hello everybody. I'm Robert Truckner.
I'm the medical director for the medical
skill assignment program here in the
state of New Mexico. Happy to join you.
>> Uh, Carmen.
Hello everybody. I'm Carmen Batista. I'm
a health educator here with the program.
>> And Katie.
>> Hi. Good afternoon everybody. My name is
Katie Fry Tag and I'm also a health
educator here with the program.
>> Okay. And so just would like on behalf
of the department to welcome everyone.
This is the committee um of the medical
psilocybin advisory board. This is the
training and education committee. And as
introduced earlier, Brenda Burgard, who
is the chair for this committee. And
with that, um, the Department of Health
is here to administratively support so
that we will help with the logistics and
other issues. Um, and, uh, as we move on
forward. Um, but Brenda, this is your
meeting and so go right on ahead. And
just a quick question, Brenda, for the
slides, would you like me to present
them and move them forward or did you
want to go ahead and present?
>> You go ahead and present it. It's
And uh so again let me introduce myself.
I am Brenda Burgard and I am a licensed
um clinical uh practitioner uh for
therapy and um here at licens in New
Mexico and part of the board of the
medical assignment advisory board. I
want to welcome everyone to this meeting
and help with participating and working
together on establishing a program for
education and training in New Mexico. So
siphon program it will be uniquely um
meeting medical safety and ethical
standards while including native and
traditional healers and other
practitioners.
And there's a lot that we need to cover
in a very very short time. And I want to
start with practitioners that are
already trained. Um so um I'm kind of
curious. Um so I want to see how many
people here today
um have been educated in uh psilocybin
training. If anybody could raise their
hand, we could just take a you know a
little number here of you know who
sought training for sil uh psilocybin or
any other psychedelic training
and maybe we could maybe you can do the
count for me Dominic.
>> Sure. So, people are still raising their
hands, but we're already at 17
uh at this point. Uh sorry, we're at 18
now. 19.
[laughter]
>> Okay. So, it looks like about 18 or 19
people. Um hand here.
>> Yeah. And that's why I'm kind of
thinking and that's with uh 30 attendees
uh outside of uh the DO team. So yeah,
that that's really wonderful to see
>> and and and still people are being
admitted. though this this is very
encouraging because um I wanted to get
an idea of how many people have been
wanting to get trained for for this and
get ready for this because I think
people kind of knew that uh New Mexico
here in the future and here we are may
be doing a program like this and uh like
myself um I always hoped and that New
Mexico would get on board with um uh
psilocybin at least to use that in in a
medical um profession. So I think this
is this is wonderful so far. So
um let me see uh let me see where I left
off. Um so there's a lot that we need to
cover in a very short time and
uh unfortunately a lot of this stuff is
dry and boring at times. I'll try to
make it as interesting as possible. Um,
uh, but we need to be thorough in our
approach to making a program that will
serve the community. And the goal here
today is to go over what is needed to
get started and to roll out guidelines
for those who have training to be the
first in line to begin the process.
Um, I know there's going to be a lot
that I left out and this is wonderful
that we're doing this in a public forum
because people can come in and add what
they need to add to uh this document
that we'll be looking at here later on.
So, uh, for right now, we'll be covering
the basics because we are also offering
this to the public too for information.
So this PowerPoint that I have is is um
fairly basic just to get an overview of
what we're going to be doing at uh the
Department of Health here and uh what
our expectations and means to deliver
these goals and additionally uh
reciprocity qualifications will be met
will fulf while fulfilling the
expectations of the DO and allowing us
to begin offering professional training
services to Mexicans. New Mexicans as we
as soon as possible. So, uh, first off,
we're going to present the basic
PowerPoint and, uh, you know, what the
subcommittee responsibilities, which is
everybody that's coming here today. Uh,
uh, reciprocity, you know, working the
working document that I'm going to be,
uh, presenting today, you know, what
those bottlenecks look like. um you know
getting ideas about how to um make this
flow uh make sure that we don't miss any
steps uh especially when it concerns
safety.
um creating a curriculum uh who's going
to be te teaching supervisors uh
practicum what all that's going to look
like um uh where will training take
place and I have a couple ideas there
too clinics colleges places of worship
or environments with the do approves and
I was thinking um I was looking at a map
of all the locations where the
department of health um has offices
throughout New Mexico. So, that's just
an idea. Maybe having something uh where
we could teach at those locations. So,
these are just some big ideas that I
have. Um but I definitely need everyone
else's input on this. So, uh the purpose
of this meeting today is uh rever review
the proposed framework for education and
training in psilocybin assisted mental
health care. uh clarify scopes and roles
and guiding principles
and align framework with the New Mexico
Department of Health advisory norms and
public health standards and identify
areas for feedback refinement and the
next steps.
Um so let's go on to the next slide
here.
Okay.
And why this framework uh exists? Uh the
purpose is create safety um ethical
culturally respect respectful
education and training support public
health community well-being
accountability align with New Mexico
Department of Health advisory standards
and prepare for evolving law research
and practice. Okay, next one.
All right.
uh what this framework covers and of
course this is just um
the basic uh overall um framework of
what we're going to be doing uh as far
as training goes. So two parts the first
part is education the foundational
knowledge for all roles.
Um part two training skills competencies
supervised practice includes practicum
um designed to support safety equity
cultural respect and regulatory
readiness.
And let's see the next slide. Okay. and
who this is for. Intended participants,
mental health clinicians, indigenous
healers and cultural practitioners,
pastors, clergy, chaplain, spiritual
care providers, death doulas, end of
life professionals, medical providers,
co-f facilitators, paraprofessionals,
and community policy and program
leaders. And the next slide,
um, guiding values, the core principles,
safety and ethics, equity, access,
cultural humility, respect,
trauma-informed care, interd
disciplinary collaboration, evidence
informed practice, and clear scope of
practice. And next
and the education overview of uh
foundational learning shared baseline
knowledge for all roles didactic and
education only not uh practice
authorization
um supports public understanding safety
informed uh participation
uh and this is required before advanced
training.
Next,
what people learn in part one, key
topics, history, cultural, context of
psilocybin,
basic brain and psychological effects,
mental health and spiritual care
applications,
safety, screening and risk awareness,
ethics, consent and power dynamics, and
legal regulatory overview.
And next okay part two training overview
skills-based training role specific
pathways supervised competencybased
builds a preparation support and
integration skills and does not expand
legal or professional scope.
training pathways, role specific tracks,
therapists and mental health clinicians,
indigenous healers and cultural
practitioners, clergy, chaplain,
spiritual care providers, death duelist,
end of life professionals, medical uh
providers and co-f facilitator co-f
facilitators and paraprofessionals.
Uh reciprocity and accountability
recognizing prior training supports
reciprocity from other states or
programs. review of certificates and
transcripts, curriculum and supervision,
lensure, ordination or endorsement and
does not override New Mexico law or
lenture
uh oversight and next steps governance
uh advisory of the New Mexico uh
department of health uh designated
oversight indigenous indigenous clinical
and medical community voices ongoing
review as evidence and policy evolve. 12
and then the next steps is community
feedback refinement and responsibility
implementation.
So I know this is a lot we're all
rolling out. It's it's like coming like
an avalanche here. And so uh this would
be a good time um to take um uh some one
minute comments here and there and then
Dominic I think we'll get into the
documentation that's been here. So, I'm
taking a little um some public views on
uh what was in the PowerPoint.
>> And we have [clears throat] someone with
their hand raised. It is uh Dr. Linda
Fatimi. Your mic is open. You can unmute
yourself.
>> Thank you so much. Thank you so much uh
Brenda for such a comprehensive um
overview. I think one of the only
comments I have um is where you had the
um slide for the death doulas and you
know having different routes of
training.
What we're finding in our academy as
it's rolling right now and it's a New
Mexico originate original original New
Mexico Academy for psychedelics um
through conscious position um is having
all these professionals together creates
such rich discussion and um
cross-pollination
of different disciplines. So it makes it
a multidisciplinary
um approach where the doctor isn't
thinking about a particular thing that
the death doula is thinking about or the
nurse or the you know uh the social
worker or the therapist and where I see
you our first responders who are h such
rich experiences that they're sharing
with us. So I think having everybody on
board together having these rich
discussions have been really awesome. uh
but I do see also some like particular
branches of programs being dedicated for
you know some hours to those particular
professions um maybe to have a more
connection in that way too. So um just
some thoughts. Thank you so much. Thank
you for that. I um I agree that um what
I'm
looking at here is attending all of our
previous meetings and seeing like you
said a cross-pollination of um
professionals and uh their specialties.
I think it's it it is very important to
have um all of this education
um laid out in a way where everyone can
um learn more about um uh psilocybin and
how it's going to be used. So, um I
don't have any like really firm ways of
doing things because this is why this is
we're having these uh meetings is uh to
get everyone's input and to change
things the way we need to and let it
flow and let it evolve uh according to
um the department of health and our our
community. So, yes, thank you so much
for uh that comment.
Um, Deb Thorne put on the chat, Dr.
Linda Fatami, as with the three training
programs I've personally received,
having a robust variety of faculty on
board is vital to delivering a solid
certification program.
>> Thank you, Deb. Thank you for your input
on that, too. I I think so, too. I think
having um uh a staff on board with uh
you know their expertise and and
professionalism uh would be would be
great to to have and incorporate all of
this into it. Absolutely. So, um I think
we're moving along here. Okay, it's 127.
Um because I want to leave time here to
go over the document as well. Um, are
there any other comments before we move
on to the document?
Watts B W B W B W B W B W B W B W B W B
W B Walton raised his hand. Let me
unmute uh allow your mic. You can unmute
yourself.
Okay. Sorry about that. I was unmuting.
Um yeah, just one comment there real
quick. Um I just want to also make sure
that um or I would suggest that we make
a pathway for people uh like myself,
first responders, EMTs
um that uh have experience in this area,
but then are also working in a peer
support role um for first responders and
um people like that. So just a
suggestion. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Thank you very much.
>> Uh, Patricia has her hand raised. Let me
You can unmute yourself, Patricia.
>> Hi, can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Okay, perfect. Um, I did want to
mention, I don't know if it's just me,
but I can't chat. It says chat is only
available during the meeting. So, I
don't know if others are having that
issue.
Um, and then Oh, did you want to say
something, Dominic? Yeah, I was just
going to say I mean we have had other
people speak in the chat so I'm not sure
what that is but um we'll see if we can
figure out what might be happening with
regard to that.
>> Okay, I can also rejoin. Um, but I also
like Paul wanted to mention um I didn't
know what you meant by
paraprofessionals. Um, but I'm someone
who is not a traditionally licensed but
um has a lot of lived experience and
studies um and done to other programs
for education. So I also just wanted to
like open that up. I don't know if
you've included that in your
considerations but for like non-medical
professionals or people that don't have
advanced formal education.
>> Oh yeah. Uh thank you uh for asking
about that. Um well
co-f facilitators and paraprofessionals
is that you don't necessarily have a
degree in anything. Um uh peer support
workers uh I've worked with peer support
workers in addiction and that required I
believe like 40 hours. So, I think as
time goes on, if people don't have um a
certificate or a degree, but would like
to be in involved and uh provide uh care
and support, I'm really looking at um
that very very closely because
uh we're going to need people that that
can co-f facilitate or uh within um a a
training program that will have people
come in with um uh just
knowing that they're going to be
learning some special skills to help uh
uh co-f facilitate or uh give some peer
support.
>> Yeah. Okay. Thank you. I guess for me
specifically, my training has been in
facilitation and that's where I have
experience. So, I just want to make the
request for people that don't have um
the like I said formal education to be
considered.
>> Can I ask you do are are you uh like do
you have a certification or
um any training in in your background
doing it?
>> I've trained in like trauma-informed
body work.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> A lot of energetic work. Yeah. And
>> even in the spiritual realm, I saw you
had a spiritual thing, so I don't know
the definition of that. Um but I just I
was just curious in that way.
Yeah. Um I would love to see that. I
would love to have uh something uh a
program implemented to include uh people
like yourself in this. Um I know of a
few people that uh would like to take
some coursework. Um
we have to determine what that will be,
but I think um this will also be
included.
>> Yeah. Okay. And I've also taken like two
formal facilitation programs. they just
aren't wonderful certification formally.
So yeah, thank you.
>> Oh, excellent. Thank you.
>> Dr. An Mets, your mics um you can unmute
yourself.
>> Great. Hi. Um my name is Dr. Anne Metsz
and I'm an LPC. Uh I live in Tal County
and I'm certified as a clinical
facilitator up in Colorado. Um, you
know, I think one thing I hope people
keep in mind that makes New Mexico's
program unique, and I think really is
something that we should try to account
for when we're coming up with a training
program, um, is the fact that everyone
who will be going through this program,
with the exception of kind of end of
life care, will have a psychiatric
condition. And so, it's a more
vulnerable population perhaps than, you
know, are necessarily coming in for
services in either Colorado or in
Oregon. And so I do think that we want
to make sure that the training is robust
enough so that the client population
that we're serving, people with the, you
know, established diagnoses are getting
appropriate care and that the people
that are working with them are, um,
adequately trained. So I'm just putting
that out there. Um, I'm glad there are
some options for co-f facilitation for
paraprofessionals. Um yeah but just want
to make sure that scope of practice is
respected within the professions.
>> Thank you doctor. Thank you for that.
>> And [clears throat]
James Brown has a you're mute. Uh you
can unmute yourself.
>> Brenda. Thank you for the giant task on.
You're so amazing. We do appreciate you
so much. Um just a couple comments on my
end today on this to start out. Um are
we looking at a non-directive approach?
Um you know, what kind of facilitation
are we going to be doing in these
programs? It's something to look at. You
know, is it non-directive? Is there
touch allowed? If there is, what is that
defined as? Um and then the other thing
um that I would like to bring up today
is like total hours. you know what are
we looking at total hours for the
curriculum itself I'm sure you guys have
an idea but that's something to discuss
and then um ongoing
there's a variety of things um ongoing
Colorado has something that's where they
uh continue the facilitations education
and is that something that we're going
to require you know as as far as for our
facilitators or our service center
owners you know are they going to be
required to,
you know, um, get hours in addition
every year to facilitation. That
one-time training is great, but I have a
big belief on continued education, um,
because it does change and we're in a a
current state of change with
psychedelics. And so I, you know, my
thing is to, you know, vote for that or
or voice my opinion towards that, you
know, continuation down the line for as
that looks. But thank you so much for
your time, everybody.
Oh, thank you. Thank you, James. And
thank you for that. Um, uh, and the
documentation that we're going to be
pulling up here, um, pretty soon, and
the reason why I kind of wanted to do
this in the middle a little bit to kind
of like spark, you know, our um,
creativity in in developing this. And of
course, yes, um, I, as a clinician, um,
every two years I have to renew my
license. I have to do at least 40 CEUs
with 12 of them being ethics. Um, I
think continuing education is a a big
part of this because as you know with
all of the developments and research uh
behind psilocybin uh there'll be more
and more things that are going to be
changing as uh we grow and learn more
about how we need to uh approach our
education and training and start to
establish that in a very um uh uh formal
way. so that uh we're meeting all of the
standards, all of the ethics, um all of
the care that we need to do to provide
uh uh our um
patients or our um uh other other people
that we need to to treat. So, um I think
you're um everyone's bringing up some
really good points here. Um this is
going to be um something that is going
to be standardized with the department
of health. So I'm hoping that um with
your input we can create a nice program
that uh will include safety. Uh yes of
course what someone was saying earlier
what is what is touch going to be? Are
we going to allow touch? Well how much
of that are we going to allow? uh what
our um what our um patients are going to
uh be comfortable with. Um it's it's
going to be a very very um um
multiple
disciplinary type of thing. But if you
yourself are a professional and you know
that you have to keep your license up
every year by taking um other classes
too, the psilocybin program should not
be any different. We should be able to
have like a training every two years
just to keep on top of this. Um, any
other questions?
We have a few hands raised, but I'm
going to read off the chat. Uh, Ellen
posted just that the training is
affordable, probably goes with equity
and access, but affordability is
crucial. And a question from Lori. How
soon do you expect a course to be
available in New Mexico?
>> Question.
I um I
I don't know at this time when exactly.
We don't really have an idea yet, but um
as Dominic has said in previous meetings
that we're trying to get this done,
right, Dominic, before um you know, this
year is out. So, this is why I'm
really jumping on all of these points
today is so that we could have a working
document that each meeting that we have,
we could go in there and uh edit it, add
to things, make adjustments, reword
things the way they need to be properly
worded. Uh what kind of standards are we
we going to be in place? And also too,
the cost of training. What is the tra
how much is this going to to cost?
Especially uh people who um are starting
from um the beginning of their training
and what how many hours um who's going
to be teaching this, where are we going
to be teaching this? So, we really need
to come together as a community to
really um uh cut through all of this and
and find uh of course this is not going
to be perfect, but we have to meet a
consensus of what this is going to be
and look at the budget and see how much
money we have in order to train people.
So, and I know training is very uh um
you know, we have to do uh uh for some
people we we would have to do a
practicum. Uh other people are um
haven't started any type of training yet
and that's what we want to establish
here in New Mexico. However, there could
be a population out there that's here in
New Mexico that's in between. They're
they're already training in other other
states. So, how is that going to how are
we going to bring those people in that
are like in between this year right now
and how are we going to um look at uh
the requirements that they are learning
that we can transfer over to here to New
Mexico. And then we have um you know
people like myself that are already
certified in in um uh uh training in
psychedelics in general. I mean some
people are trained in ketamine, some
people are trained in MDMA, some people
are trained in um uh psilocybin and and
various other things. And then we have
traditional uh trainings as well uh and
uh what what that's going to look like.
How are we going to prove this to the uh
and appease the uh uh the department of
health and make that so that um
everybody has met requirements for
safety and ethics and etc.
And uh just to add into that, Brenda, uh
this is Dominic for those who may be
just on their phones and can't see who's
speaking, but um there's a lot of
messages in the chat if the trainings
will involve various other items, if
they're being modeled after specific
programs, you know, different
definitions, things like that. And
remember, that's exactly what this is
for. We have not predetermined what
types of training are required. These
are ideas. Some of these are just
starting points as we move through this.
And so if you have suggestions or ideas
about particular types of trainings or
models, you know, that's the sort of
thing to be proposing as the meetings
move forward. Um but this is the idea is
that we um we want to ensure that we're
getting as many ideas that we can and to
sort of sift through them and not to
necessarily be um uh not necessarily to
have predetermined ideas because
sometimes the things that are most
important are the things that just sort
of arrive organically and naturally. And
so we want to make sure to have that.
And for those who are saying where to
put these items, uh we will be having
links that we are going to be putting up
into um the chat a little bit later on
how to reach the program and uh where
you can send information and items and
how to do so. So just uh for everybody's
uh information on that, we will post
that here shortly.
>> Thank you, Dominic. Thank you for that.
So, um,
>> do you want me to, um, the raised hands?
I have two more.
>> Okay, go ahead.
>> James, you can unmute yourself.
>> Hello. Can everybody hear me? All right.
>> Yes.
>> Hi. Good afternoon, Brenda. Thank you so
much for doing an amazing opening and I
really appreciate the comprehensive work
that you've done. Uh, one thing I would
really recommend and I think I've spoken
about it in a previous meeting, but was
a recommendation for a centralized
registry to track individuals that are
delivering psilocybin services. Um I'm
just going to bring up um you know there
is a uh incident with a phase 2 MDMA
assisted psychotherapy that was
conducted by MAPS and I personally
believe that there were boundary
violations that occurred and a
facilitator registry would really help
ensure earlier detection transparency
and making sure that appropriate actions
are um being followed up. I think it's
super important that we protect the
patients that need it the most and harm
reduction is absolutely imperative where
human beings and um certain people might
have nefarious behaviors um and there's
certainly a power dynamic involved with
psychedelics specifically psilocybin
so I would really appreciate any
thoughts or comments regarding this idea
um thank you very much for your time
>> thank you James I'm very well aware of
that um incident and um this is this is
something that happens in many
professions where um there are uh
unscrupulous people that you know um
kind of fall through the cracks and
don't are not um held um or are not uh
had a sufficient background check or
something. It's it's it's a new incident
that happens. But I think a registry is
is an interesting idea. Um I I haven't
thought about that. Um but yeah, we
might want to uh take a close look at
that as well. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much. And it's
interesting going back to that touch
conversation. Just because somebody
consents for touch when prior to their
um session, they might change their mind
while they're in the actual session. And
so I think you even defining what a hug
is. A hug standing up is very different
from what a hug is st laying down.
[laughter]
So um just some points to really
consider. Thank you again.
>> Well, thank you. I think these uh what
you brought up is very very important
because especially um uh those in the
professions of somatic healing or um
masseuse or any even uh medical doctors.
Uh you know touch is a very um uh
interesting subject to get into with um
uh discussing that with uh with a
client. uh and some people have uh a lot
of trauma around touch. So, uh thank you
for that, James.
>> Shane, your mic's unmuted. You can uh
unmute yourself.
>> Yeah, I don't I had to step out for a
second. I had to restart my computer
because I was it [clears throat] wasn't
allowing me to type anything into the
chat. But um so I don't know if this has
been covered, but are we going to have a
process where we submit like I I'm
certified through um being true to
yourself uh an organiza an organization
out of Colorado as a integration coach.
Um they're recognized by Oregon and by
Colorado already. So I'm assuming
they'll be recognized by New Mexico. But
how would we submit
our certification to see that it's going
to be approved and then how long would
that approval or do we know yet how long
that approval process will take?
>> Well, uh we we don't know anything uh as
yet. I mean I uh in the document that um
maybe this would be a good time um after
we're done with all the questions bring
up the document that I wrote. Um of
course this isn't all in this is not in
stone yet. um saying that it would be um
but this is for uh us to go in there and
uh uh really edit and u modify it the
way it it needs to be. I think when it
comes to recognizing
um like u certain um curriculum for
instance uh how that would transfer to
what New Mexico wants um and and and
needs as far as um uh uh transferring
any like I'm not saying credits or
anything like that but um you know just
having like a transfer of uh what
someone has gone through in training and
education. Uh we'll be taking I think a
close look at that.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Uh anyone else?
I
>> think that's it for now.
>> Okay. Um Donna, do you want to bring up
the uh the um document? I am doing. So
give it just the system just a minute to
come up
>> and
>> just so everybody knows the text may be
a little small when it first comes up. I
will be expanding it. Um and hopefully
now everyone can see it. Can people see
the document?
Yes. Okay. I'm seeing some thumbs up.
Thank you. Okay.
And Brenda, how would you like to go
through this? Would you like me to go
ahead and read as we go through the
sections?
>> Uh, if you like, if you're not too tired
yet, [laughter]
>> not a problem at all. And so this is the
education and training psilocybin
committee working document. And the
purpose of the document is to provide
professional collaborative framework to
guide a committee in developing the
educational standards and foundational
knowledge related to psilocybin assisted
mental health care. And the second part
of that is training pathways, compet
competency development and supervised
practice models for therapists, death
doulas, medical professionals,
indigenous healers, pastors, clergy, and
spiritual care providers and co-f
facilitators, paraprofessionals.
The framework is designed to align with
New Mexico Department of Health advisory
board norms and public health standards.
Support portability and reciprocity.
Reciprocity for qualified professionals
trained in other jurisdictions.
Provide sufficient structure for program
approval, funding, and oversight while
remaining adaptable as evidence and
regulation invol evolve. The intent is
to support ethical, culturally
responsive, traumainformed, and
evidenceinformed approaches while
respecting indigenous knowledge systems,
spiritual care traditions, professional
scopes of practice, and evolving
statutory and regulatory requirements.
And I'll stop there in case there's
questions so far.
>> Okay, I think we have one question.
>> There is a hand raised.
>> Ellen, you can unmute yourself.
>> Thanks. Um, my question is just about
the terminology mental health care. I
don't I mean I understand that most of
what we're looking at is mental health
care but obviously the research is
changing and it was my understanding
that we would continue to really explore
um pain issues and and some of the other
things that um psilocybin being used for
and even end of life um care may or may
not be considered actually I know it's a
lot of times anxiety driven but it's not
necessarily mental health care and is it
do we is that terminology something that
we want to consider. Is it psilocybin
assisted care or psilocybin assisted
therapy or something that maybe isn't
like mental health specific things?
>> Good question, uh, Dominic. Um, so I
think what we're trying to do, um, at
this moment is, uh,
we could include it. What do you think,
Dominic? Do we could we
>> I I think the question Ellen is trying
to get at and Ellen I don't mean to put
words in your mouth and please correct
me if I am incorrect is just really that
it should be knowledge related to
psilocybin assisted care that it
shouldn't just be limited necessarily to
mental health because there could be
other conditions down the road such as
pain or uh other you know sematic type
issues or body issues and uh so just
really to take that portion out if that
makes sense. Am I correct on that?
>> Yes, that's what I was saying.
>> Perfect. So, really just striking that
part of it, taking the mental health out
and just leaving it as psilocybin
assisted care.
>> Thank you. Thank you for that.
Um because I too work with uh many
people who are homebound
uh and deal with a lot of pain issues
and um yeah, mental and physical are
intertwined. However, um yes, psilocybin
could definitely work with um
uh physical issues as well. Thank you.
>> Okay. Uh so continuing on to the guiding
principles, all education and training
developed under this framework should
align with the following principles.
Safety and ethics, prioritizing
physical, psychological, cultural,
spiritual, and moral safety. Equity and
access, reducing barriers for
historically marginalized communities.
Cultural humility and respect. Honoring
indigenous knowledge, sovereignty,
lineage-based practices, and diverse
spiritual traditions. Traumainformed
care, recognizing the prevalence of
trauma and avoiding reharm.
Interdisciplinary collaboration
valuing distinct clinical, spiritual,
cultural, and community roles while
fostering shared understanding.
Evidence informed practice integrating
research and data, lived experience,
clinical wisdom and pastoral spiritual
care frameworks.
Scope of practice clarity. clear
boundaries based on lenture, ordination,
certification and role. And I'll pause
there in case there are any questions.
Okay. Uh I don't see any so I will
continue on. Um so for the educational
piece um and uh I will just go through
this but if we do have the mental health
care uh portion in here we can edit that
on as we move forward. So if I do read
that and it's specific on there just
know we'll we'll work on editing that
portion. So part one overview part one
establishes shared foundational
knowledge for all participants
regardless of professional background.
Education is didactic in nature and does
not authorize clinical facilitation or
sacramental practice. Target audience
psychotherapists and mental health
clinicians, indigenous healers and
cultural practitioners,
pastors, clergy, chaplain and spiritual
care providers, death doulas and end of
life professionals,
physicians and medical providers,
paraprofessionals and co-f facilitators,
policy makers, administrators and
program staff, optional first
responders, EMTs, law enforcement,
firefighters, etc.
Part one, learning objectives.
Participants completing part one
education should be able to describe the
historical, cultural, spiritual, and
contemporary use of psilocybin.
Understand basic neurobiological and
psychological mechanisms of action.
Identify indicators, contraindications,
and risk factors.
>> [snorts]
>> Explain ethical considerations, informed
consent, and power dynamics.
Recognize the role of set, setting,
preparation, ritual, and integration.
Understand legal and regulatory
frameworks relevant to their
jurisdiction and role.
And uh just to uh a comment that's in
the chat from Shane about where would
integration coaches fit. I think uh
Shane that would depend on what other
potential lensures they may have because
they may actually be potentially in
different categories. For example, they
might be in paraprofessional. They also
may be in a medical professional
category. So I think it would depend if
they have other uh lensures uh as well.
Okay, I'll move on to the next set. Part
one, the core educational domains,
history and cultural context.
>> There is a question.
>> It great. Go on ahead.
>> So, in the chat, Shane put, "Where would
integration coaches fit in the target
audience list?"
>> Yeah. I had already answered that,
Carmen.
>> Okay. Oh, sorry. And I'm unmuting uh
James, you can unmute yourself, James.
Hey Dominic, on that one, does it say
medical providers or is it medical
professionals? I wasn't sure if it I
just want to make sure that clarified.
>> It says uh providers. Yeah.
>> Right. So, I want to make sure that my
thought was to add professionals just so
that we could include
other other people there. That's all.
>> Absolutely. Not a problem.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah. Thank you, James. Okay. Uh,
educational domains, history and
cultural context, indigenous and
ceremonial use of psilocybin containing
mushrooms, spiritual, sacramental and
contemplative frameworks across
cultures. Impact of colonization,
[snorts]
criminalization and prohibition,
contemporary medical, spiritual and
decriminalization movements. Ethical
issues related to cultural and spiritual
appribation.
Neuroscience and psychology,
pharmarmacology and neurobiology of
psilocybin. effects on perception,
emotion, cognition, spirituality, and
sense of self. Therapeutic and meaning
making mechanisms for example
neuroplasticity insight and ext
existential processing
mental health and spiritual care
applications depression anxiety PTSD end
of life distress addiction trauma moral
injury and ex uh existential suffering
current research evidence and
limitations
and the interfaces between
psychotherapy, spiritual counseling,
cultural and pastoral care,
safety screening and risk mitigation,
psychological and medical
contraindications,
medication interactions, adverse events
and crisis response basics, referral
pathways between or among clinical,
medical and spiritual care providers.
Ethics, consent, and power dynamics.
Informed consent,
uh, sorry, informed consent models
across clinical and nonclinical roles,
dual relationships and boundary
management, vulnerability during
non-ordinary and spiritual significant
states, consent for touch, preferences
within ethical boundaries.
Uh and just to check in the chat, I did
uh miss a little here. Jamie asking is
there a role for pharmacist? I think
that would fall in under the medical uh
professionals uh aspect on that at this
time. Um and change to uh LN2 health
care professionals to include that. Um
nurses and nurse practitioners are
technically not medical. Again, I think
in a broader term from a department of
health standpoint, we do actually
consider them to be medical. So, I'm not
sure that change needs to be there, but
that's something this group can decide.
Um, and uh it's going to be important to
get clear about if this is non-directive
approach with the language about
spiritual and the boundaries around
this. So, I think we have that there.
Um, and then Deb, sorry I can't see uh
that uh that little post there uh having
a definition.
Sorry, it's an image that has the
defining clinicians and actually
includes that in there. And again, uh
just as a reminder to everybody, um what
this really is doing is it's setting
sort of the framework. And so as we
start going through more of this and we
start looking at it, there are those
definitions can be added in so that has
in information as far as who is
considered exactly professionals, what
which language specifically to use. This
is really more of an overall general
general framework on that with regard to
that. And I do see Deb has her hand
raised. So Carmen, if you could unmute
Deb uh and then let Deb speak.
Carmen had to step out for a second. I
can do that. Uh Deb, your mic has been
enabled. Please speak when unmute your
cell when you're ready.
Deb, your mic isn't enabled. Please
unmute yourself when you're ready to
speak.
I think she put in the chat that she
would share via email. I think that okay
defining clinicians. I think that's what
she was trying to say.
>> Perfect. Thank you, Dad.
>> Yeah. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Okay.
Um legal and regulatory overview are
federal versus state law considerations,
professional licensing, ordination and
institutional accountability
implications, documentation and
reporting requirements as applicable.
The part one educational methods,
lectures and seminars, live and
asynchronous, assigned readings and
multimedia resources, case examples and
facilitated discussion panels including
indigenous spiritual community and lived
experience voices, knowledge checks and
reflective exercises, non-punitive
documentation and completion standards.
Certificate of completion documenting
hours and domains covered attestation of
participation and adherence to ethical
standards. Documentation suitable for
regulatory review funding compliance or
reciprocity evaluation.
Uh and that's the end of uh and again
remember everybody this is just a
beginning. There are other things that
I'm sure as the discussions go on that
can be added on in. Um and one of the
things just as we go through uh and we
pull for example the minutes and
information from the chat you know
that's the kind of those are the kinds
of informations even if we don't call it
out specifically um verbally that we do
look at as far as for addition into
various documents and items. So even if
we miss something we do uh in the
meeting we do go back to review to make
sure that we're including everything.
Any questions so far up to this point?
Okay. So, training uh skills-based
training, competency development, and
supervised uh practice.
Part two overview. The part two focuses
on skills-based training and competency
development. Participation in part two
requires completion of part one or an
approved equivalent and adherence to
role specific eligibility criteria.
Training does not imply authorization
beyond legal, professional, or spiritual
scope of practice.
Training tracks. Training pathways
should be tailored while maintaining
shared core competencies. Tracks may
overlap through interdisciplinary
collaboration while maintaining scope of
practice boundaries.
Psychotherapists and mental health
clinicians, licensed or licensed
eligible professionals,
uh, indigenous healers and cultural
practitioners recognized by community,
nation, PBLO, tribe or lineage.
Participation deter defined by
self-determination, sovereignty, and
protection of cultural knowledge.
Pastors, clergy, chaplain, and spiritual
care providers ordained, endorsed, or
formally recognized by a faith tradition
or spiritual community. practice limited
to spiritual counseling, pastoral care,
and religious or existential support.
Participation does not authorize medical
or psychotherrapeutic practice.
death doulas and endof life
professionals certified licensed or
community recognized practitioners
physicians and medical providers MDO and
PPA or equivalent
co-f facilitators paraprofessionals
individuals supporting preparation
session support and integration under
defined supervision
uh and then uh next section is core
training competencies all tracks Oh, and
I do see that we have a hand raised.
>> James, your mic's been um enabled. You
can unmute yourself.
>> Thank you again. And and Dominic and
Brenda, back to that language prior
right there. Would it be again medical
professionals right there again?
>> And then would we open that up to like
again the RNs, the pharmacists, others
that are those professionals per se? And
James, as I said, will go through and
edit to ensure that language is
consistent throughout. That's uh yeah,
it just uh trying to do it on the fly
while reading just is not always going
to happen.
>> You do this, Dominic. [laughter]
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah,
>> it was more my ADD kicking. Sorry.
>> Sure. Not a problem. And I totally get
it. And uh and I appreciate it, too. And
in fact, now the great part, as I
mentioned before, we do go back through
to pick the comments. So now when we get
to this part uh as we go through it'll
be the reminder in case we missed it.
[laughter]
Uh and then I do see in the comment
there's a couple of items uh which just
to sort of do this is are about
practicums and about um diagnosis
ensuring there's information about that
um to be able to to be able to um
include that and for a definition of
spiritual community. Um and just as a
note all of these will actually need to
be defined. Some of them uh may already
have other definitions in regulation and
law for example MDs uh LPNs that sort of
thing from a lensure but things that do
not will need to get definitions. So
it's a great a a great question and one
of the ones that at a perhaps a future
meeting can be what exactly are these
definitions
and similar with regard to you know uh
the addition of things like
traumainformed and sematic practitioners
that sort of uh listings.
Okay. So uh core training competencies,
preparation skills, establishing trust
and alliance within role boundaries,
psychoeducation and expectation setting,
cultural, spiritual and existential
preparation considerations,
facilitation and support, presence,
nondirective support and attunement,
managing challenging psychological or
spiritual experiences,
somatic and grounding techniques. Techqu
integration support, meaning making and
narrative processing,
supporting values-based and behavioral
change, referral and continuity of care
across discipline,
ethics and professional conduct, scope
of practice, boundaries, confidentiality
and documentation,
power, transparence, counter
transparence, and spiritual authority.
uh role specific training elements. Oh,
and before I do that, uh just another um
item uh Denali, they are not ne
necessarily intended to be exhaustive at
the moment and noted about the DOM to be
included.
Um so role specific training elements,
psychotherapists,
clinical assessment and treatment
planning, trauma sensitive
interventions,
integration with ongoing psychotherapy,
indigenous healers, protection of
ceremonial knowledge, community
accountability structures, optional
[snorts]
interfaces with western systems,
pastors, clergy, chaplain, spiritual
assessment and pastoral presence.
Supporting faith-based existential and
moral meaning making navigating
spiritual crisis, discernment and
integration, ethical boundaries between
pastoral care and psychotherapy.
Death doulas, existential and spiritual
distress support, family systems and
caregiver inclusion, end of life
integration practices,
medical providers, medical screening and
clearance, monitoring psychological or
I'm sorry, physiological responses,
coordination with mental health and
spiritual care providers.
Uh, am I missing anything in the chat?
Sorry. When I have to go back and forth
between two screens, it takes me a
moment for my eyes to adjust. Uh, I do
not see anything else in the chat. Any
hands raised? I don't see any hands
raised. Okay. Uh, training methods,
experiential learning, non-drug-based
unless legally authorized, supervised
practicum, mentorship or apprentice
models, case consultation. Oh, sorry,
Brenda. Uh maybe we could put in the
training um uh practicum uh because I
think I I
did not put anything in the training
methods for practicum.
So maybe we can add Yeah.
>> Uh oh, you do have it. It's a second
bullet.
>> Oh, the second Okay.
>> It's a supervised practicum.
>> Okay.
>> So, thank you.
>> Yeah, I missed it. I wrote so much that
it's like [laughter] it's a lot. Thank
you. It
>> It is a lot. It's a good outline and uh
yeah and uh uh it's easy to miss and
actually somebody earlier had had a I
think it was Katherine had mentioned
about making sure that there was
practicum uh in there or it may have
been Deb. I'm not really sure who uh
that was quite a bit back. Oh, Deb has
about mentorships which I think uh that
may be something to add on in. Um oh
actually it is there right after
practicum. So uh that is there. So yeah,
uh anyway, uh so I'll start on that line
because I forgot exactly where I was,
but uh supervised practicum, mentorships
or apprentice, apprenticeship models,
case consultation and interdisciplinary
learning groups, reflective practice,
ethics review and selfassessment,
clear documentation of hours,
competencies, and supervision.
Reciprocity and recognition of prior
training. This framework supports
reciprocity pathways for clinicians,
medical providers and spiritual care
professionals with prior psychedelic
related education or training completed
in other jurisdiction.
Documentation for reciprocity
reciprocity review i.e. umbrella of
proof.
Certificates of completion or
transcripts, training syllabi or
curriculum outlines, documentation of
supervised practice or pctoral pastoral
training where applicable.
Professional license, ordination or
endorsement verification,
attestation of adherence to ethical and
safety standards. Reciprocity does not
supersede New Mexico lensure
requirements, statutory authority, or
scope of practice limitations.
Governance and oversight.
Oversight by an advisory board, steering
committee or NMDOH designated body.
Inclusion of indigenous, clinical,
medical, spiritual, and community
representatives,
transparent conflict of interest
policies, regular review and updates
based on emerging evidence, community
feedback, and regulatory changes.
And just as the final note on this, this
document is intended as a collaborative
foundation, does not replace legal,
medical, spiritual, or professional
regulatory guidance. I would also say
that this is a a good basis to start and
uh that these are different ideas and
there will be more um and uh we will see
as far as for doing that um and Deb
that's a a great comment with regard to
interpretation with regard to ASL and as
necessary um and uh you know it's not
just even with regard to ASL but also
other languages uh needed in in addition
to that. So, thank you for that.
Okay. And Brenda, back to you.
>> Okay. So, um uh I'm going to leave this
open. Um there's a lot uh we could go
back on to the chats here to see if
there's anything else we need to put in
here. Um
let's see. I'm kind of scrolling back
here.
Brenda, if I may make a a um just a
suggestion because this is really
introducing this to everybody and I
think there's a lot of conversation in
the chat and I don't think we'd be able
to get through it all in the time we
have remaining. What I would recommend
is just more about maybe some of the
ideas on it. And what we can do is we
can get this documented, this document
posted in the next few days so that
people can then review it and come to
the next meeting with um, you know, more
defined ideas rather than, you know, us
kind of going back and forth on lots of
different potentials and ideas. Changes
in language are important and I want to
recognize that, but we want to have some
of those discussions, but give people
time to actually absorb the information.
And so I would suggest keeping this a
little more presentation and the next
meeting be a little more about diving in
to some of those details and seeing what
we missed because I'll say there's a lot
in the chat that we can add in that
right now is not here and and I would
like to be able to recognize that.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> We do have a hand up. Uh James,
>> James, you're
>> Hello everyone again. Sorry.
>> Uh one thing I would say is uh
disabilities. I don't see anything on
here about uh we run into that with the
other programs where you have people
with uh hearing disability or other
disabilities for that. I didn't know if
that needed to be added somewhere in the
program. I just it was just an idea on
that. So that was that's all I got so
far. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Accommodations. Yes.
>> Yes. Accommodations. There you go.
>> Dr. Linda, uh, your mic has been
enabled. You can unmute yourself.
>> Thank you so much. I think, you know,
going off what James was also saying,
disabilities. I see all of my patients
are disabled and I know I've brought
this back you know um at the end of life
committee as well but they are disabled
and so the consideration there is very
important and then you know for
facilitators who have been um certified
to um also navigate if for these
patients to go to their homes or their
place of comfort where they can't get
out of the home or their own bed. Um, so
I think that should be a consideration
for sure because this is a big
population and we have a very um very
much an older population, retired
population and and a big end of life
population here.
>> Thank you for that. That's very very
important.
Hey,
do we have others with uh
uh for comments?
By the way, I didn't mean to stifle
comments. I I mean I think we should
hear them. I just uh I think trying to
change the document right now while
people are still absorbing it because
there's a lot of it and uh and we want
to make sure people are able to actually
review it and consider uh their thoughts
on it.
Ellen, your mic has been enabled. You
can unmute yourself.
>> Thanks. I know I put this in the chat,
but I just wanted to maybe bring up
having some um way to train students
because that's one of the things that I
don't see um happening right now in
Colorado or Oregon is um I really think
that it would help to have at least some
sort of a pathway
um and and again what students in
particular it's I don't know that we
need to necessarily define any of that
but just really having some sort of a
pathway um to do some educ education
with students. So, not people who are
practitioners or clinicians now, but um
really building the next generation.
Lisa, your mic has been enabled. You can
unmute yourself.
Hi. Um, I wanted to actually second that
I I do believe that, you know, anyone
who qualifies, I know you're defining
who qualifies, um, should be able to be
trained. Their difference between
training people and licensing people.
Um, we have a lot of people from all
kinds of backgrounds that come through
our training program here in Oregon and
in Colorado. And, um, and then it's up
to them what their path is. And some
people are studying to be credentialed
and some people are already
credentialed. So I think it opens up the
doorway as she mentioned. Um and I also
mentioned this in the chat but just like
I would love to see some clarity around
the spirituality cuz I do love and
appreciate that this is a part of the
conversation and with the non-directive
approach um if that is the direction
that the training programs are going
towards. um which I do agree is is is a
good one. You know, it really helps to
mitigate um issues where people become
manipulative in with people with
vulnerable states, whether they do it
purposely or unconsciously. Um that that
somehow someway that there's um clear
boundaries around how that is,
you know, discussed or taught or
something around it. I don't know what
that looks like, but I just wanted to
name it because it kept coming up for me
as the word spiritual is used and
nondirective and um just wanted to help
support clarity, however that happens.
Thank you,
>> Patricia. Your mic has been enabled. You
can unmute yourself.
>> Hi, thank you again. Um, I really like
the idea that Dominic mentioned about,
you know, taking focus topics and I
wanted to ask the question is would it
be possible to kind of schedule or know
like this date we're talking about this
category or this category and that way
um for those that can't always join can
kind of plan around that or just sort of
know what we might want to prepare to
share.
James, your mic has been enabled. You
can unmute yourself.
>> Hello everyone again. Um just my thought
again on this uh Brenda and Dom um and
team um really is behind access again.
you know, as we go through these steps
and as we go through these documents, I
want to make sure everybody is um, you
know, refocusing back on that
individual,
you know, training facility as far as we
need some standards that every training
facility will be able to provide those
standards and I'm sure we'll create
those. But just to think about also when
we're doing this the person,
you know, we have a we have a bunch of
different we have the four different um
modalities we can treat and with that
you know is there anything I like with
Dr. Fatima brought up earlier about just
again to echo that on specifics per
disease state. I think it's going to be
very specific that each is going to need
its own um educational uh objectives of
course and just to focus back on that
again and then also again about access
across the state. There's a lot of
providers in rural areas here in New
Mexico that we needed them to have
access virtually of course um but also
with that practicum, you know, when
they're thinking about where these
practicums going to be held and access
to those practicums and the total cost
to that individual. Again, we're New
Mexico, you know, besides the equity
funds. How else can we do this, you
know, and how else can we continue?
Again, I like that um continuation
long-term thought. you know, we're doing
this for the future of New Mexicans and
everybody else. So, thank you.
>> And Jen Romero had a a question. Which
committee will be working on community
education and outreach? That is once the
program is up and running, how will New
Mexicans eligible for the program be
informed and enga engaged with
And then Deb um also question would the
program allow psilocybin use for the
practicum.
These are really really good questions.
Um, and we're uh we're I I love that
we're diving in so deeply even in this
first meeting uh to really uh take a
good close look at how everything's
going to start to evolve and and work
out or not work out. Um I think when
we're talking about um the community
as a whole and educating and training um
I think uh as things evolve will those
things will start to um come into focus
especially with um you know how money
will be spent who will be training um I
I think how things will be trained um is
uh something to discussed in other
meetings. I I mean I've worked up a um a
you know a rubric even on uh training
and education here. So I I I mean these
things are going to start to uh
culminate as we talk more and more about
it. Of course we're not going to um
please everybody. Uh but uh this is a
start and this is where we're going to
be making it a a New Mexico
program and we're we're lucky that a lot
of people come uh a lot of states have
done this before us and that we can
extrapolate some of that information and
and and and um put it with ours. But
again, we've we have uh a very unique
community here of people collaborating
uh and including everybody and trying to
make this as accessible to um the the
patients and the clients as we move
forward. And I really like what what
James was saying earlier about the
future. You know, as we move along,
things are going to evolve and things
are going to change. We may even have
even stricter regulations or maybe
looser regulations. We have to see how
this is going to um evolve and shape.
And I appreciate everyone uh you know
saying what they need to say and adding
in into this program.
Have a
hand up. Marcy, your mute has been uh
your mic has been enabled. You can
unmute yourself.
Marcy push she's having mic is uh she
can't unmute herself.
Okay. If there's anyone else who would
like to speak we can move to them and
then Marcy if you like we can try again
in a minute.
And if not, you can always put your
comment in the chat. I also did include
just a minute, a couple of minutes ago
that if uh for whatever reason you're
not able to unmute, and this goes for
anybody or you just don't want to speak
in such a large public meeting, you are
welcome to send the written public
comment to the program. And I included
the email there. The only thing we do
ask is please remember to include your
full legal name, any organizational
affiliations you're representing or may
be representing. And then if you're
referencing documents from other
sources, you do not need to include the
whole document, just a working hyper
hyperlink and explain the context. And I
say that because in the past some of the
uh the documents that we've gotten have
been for example the full list of
Oregon's um you know uh rules and
regulations which are quite lengthy and
we want to actually cite the specific
area that you may be talking about or
including uh in order to help us and not
just say here's the regulations take all
of them. you know, let us know what what
areas you think are good, what you think
is bad, uh you know, what could be
improved upon, you know, and um and then
we can take it from there. But we do ask
not to include lengthy documents um just
as text. Um we have had that happen and
that creates issues for being able to
post it for people because then what
occurs is individuals go to read it and
they just get overwhelmed with the
amount of information. Um, and that's a
part of what we're trying to do here is
trying to reduce things down and have
starting points so that individuals can
actually engage [snorts] and uh make
sure that they can do things really
well.
I have a question that I'd like to um
pose to everyone out there. um
we're going to need teachers
um as well to teach these uh curriculums
and um I just want to know just a raise
of hands um who's ever been in a
position where uh they've taught um
anything in psychedelics or psilocybin
or anything like that.
So far we have about eight people who've
raised their hands. Brenda.
>> Oh, okay. Wonderful. That's that's
fantastic. And maybe
>> make it nine. Sorry. [laughter]
>> Well, you know, maybe maybe some people
would be interested in um uh knowing how
to become a teacher. uh you know we've
been concentrating on you know this
document about what we need to have in
training and education but um you know
maybe having a course especially for
those teachers uh here in New Mexico uh
that you know we could all get uh the
training because even people in the do
for would want to take a course from one
of our own
and I have a um you know I do have
another document I'm still kind of
working it out and I've been attending
all of the other meetings too and um one
thing I think that is probably one of
the uh many important things is uh where
we'll be teaching will we'll be teaching
at the universities will we be teaching
at community centers or churches, you
know, um having a place to do this in
and um you know, how much is that going
to cost or those types of things. So um
I think that's really you know part of
that is up to uh the department of
health to u kind of find out what what
we can do as far as where these you know
where we can get the knowledge and and
certified or taught or however this is
going to play out.
James, your mic has been enabled. You
can unmute yourself.
Brenda, glory, question actually. I you
know my just my thought here, I've just
given it to you guys is um I think it
the industry is going to drive some of
this. Um there's most programs out there
right now are virtual. Um the program I
attended for the path therapy was a
virtual program. The practicum is where
you come in person. So that's where I am
you know kind of voicing my my
experiences with this is that again
we're living in New Mexico. It's very
rural but people do have virtual
ability. [snorts]
And so you know some if if they if the
institution wants to have a brick and
mortar great but that's very costly and
that's up to them. Everybody's not going
to be able to go there. But if you have
a virtual option,
so I just I'm just going for both
options. If they want to again have
brick and mortar, let that happen. But
my idea is to have that virtual option
for people um and the schools to open up
virtually if they so choose. And so I
just wanted to kind of voice that out
there. That's how I've kind of seen the
different programs between um you know,
Emerald Valley Institute, uh Interrek,
IPI,
all all these programs. They're all
virtual. Um, and so I just wanted to
throw that out there is I'd like to see
that option for us in New Mexico as
well.
>> Thank you, James.
>> Dr. Latenique,
your mic has been enabled. You can
unmute yourself.
>> Thank you so much. Yeah, I second that.
Uh, what James is sharing. you know, in
our academy, what we're experiencing is
um having both in-person and virtual
during our live sessions has been very
powerful because the in-person sessions
are, you know, a few people show up each
time, but that interpersonal connection,
the wisdom sharing that happens in
person is quite powerful. Um, and then
we have people from all over the country
who um are able to also and all over New
Mexico, uh, from north to south and all
all over are able to, um, zoom in as
well. And then they have access to
replay and, you know, we're CME approved
through UNM School of Medicine. So,
they're able to get that wherever they
are. But I think that, you know, having
options is important, especially for our
more remote areas. Um and having the
in-person is very important. Uh
community building and that those
heartfelt connections are so much
stronger when we are in uh in the
presence of each other.
>> Thank you.
Um in the comments um Ellen Shiml said
um will pract practicum be experiential
as well? I think that also too um
that's
yeah I I wouldn't exclude that. Um
definitely it would be in the practicum
because a lot you don't know what it
what uh is going to come up in in um
your patient or um uh client. So yeah, I
I don't see why it would be not wouldn't
be I think it would be an essential part
of um a practicum.
Uh definitely. Um I think uh this would
be um I I think we we really don't know
quite yet about how all of this is going
to look, but uh yeah um I'm a a telealth
counselor and um I have clients all over
New Mexico. So um a lot of people cannot
uh come to um you know their town or
you know a a city because of uh
transportation issues and that uh also
too disabilities is like that too. I
mean there's people that can't leave
their home because of their disability.
So, um I see that uh we'll probably be
um actually being in homes with people.
Um and that's that's an option that we
should look at definitely. Um
uh let's see. Uh Katherine Waro says, "I
think that practicum should uh be
included both dosing and develop
personal relationship with the medicine
and guiding others." It's that's uh
wonderful. Uh yeah, absolutely.
Um,
so let's see. Um, anything else that we
could, you know, uh, cover here? Oh, I I
wanted to ask you, Dominic, um, since,
uh, we are not going to be meeting, uh,
in February for our um,
I'm I'm losing my mind here, losing my
train of thought. Um, when will our next
meeting be? Well, that's actually a
great question and that really is up to
you and as far as for the committee um
and uh the one thing that we have
request for some of the um the
committees that uh where we don't need
to have the regulations immediately, we
are focusing on cultivation and testing
because and just for those who have not
been in some of those other committees
where we've talked about it from a
timeline perspective for us to be able
to have medicine for for example for
some of the training potentially and
with regard to uh for patients by next
December, we need to have the the
cultivation and testing has to occur
first. So, we're prioritizing that
aspect of it so that we can get that out
there, get um some of those uh potential
cultivators, for example, permitted uh
because it takes time for them to be
able to um you know, to be able to
cultivate. It's not something that we
just say this cultivator is permitted
and suddenly they have uh you know
psilocybin mushrooms. It doesn't happen
that way unfortunately. And so we're
going to have that time. So we're
working on that. So what we've just
asked is that the committees um just
wait until after session because that
will give us some additional time to be
able to work through some things. Things
like this document will be able to post
it and people will have enough time to
be able to consider it. So, what I would
recommend, um, Brenda, is I would
recommend, and sorry, I'm pulling my
calendar up while I'm talking here.
>> Um, is, um, potentially either, uh,
looking at the first week or second week
of March. Um, and we do have a couple of
meetings that are already scheduled. Um,
but, you know, we can definitely work
around that. If you wanted to keep this
same time on a Friday, Friday, March 6th
from 1 to 3 is open. if you wanted to go
with that or we could look at uh later
dates or other dates even. It doesn't
necessarily need to be on Friday, but I
will leave that to you to propose.
>> That's perfect. Um uh March 6 at 1 would
be uh perfect. That would give us um
enough time to um think about it. Um I
really love that idea because uh do you
want the rough draft still on the 13th
to be posted?
uh that is the the rough draft on the
13th is actually regarding to
cultivation and testing. So you don't
need uh for this committee that's just
cultivation and testing. Uh and for
those who may have missed it in the main
uh the the the primary advisory board
meeting is we're working on a rough
draft for um with regard to the
propagation and that's actually was
presented in the propagation committee
will be up on uh the website shortly. Um
and um what we're just doing is we're
doing a rough draft with regard to that
portion, the outline of what the rules
and regulations will sort of look like.
Um and so that can be considered over
the next few weeks. But uh and we'll do
the same with regard to the document
that was presented today. That'll get
posted up in the next few uh business
days so people can consider it for the
meeting on let me make sure I have it.
Friday, March 6th between 1 and 3:00.
That's perfect. Thank you so much for
that. I really appreciate all the work
that you're doing, Dominic, and everyone
else. Um, this has been uh really a
great uh meeting. Um, sorry I was late.
I was having technical difficulties
getting
in there and doing this and my phone was
just going off like crazy because I'm in
the these signal groups. Where are you,
brother? What? Where are you? Uh so um I
apologize for that. Um uh usually I'm in
these meetings. No problem. I can get
in. No problem. Just so happens that and
I think we were having that yesterday a
little bit with um uh with Larry's uh
meeting as well. So um yeah, the you
know, these are technical um you know,
bumps in the road, but at least we all
got here. And I really appreciate
everyone coming here today. and uh
giving a voice to this and uh this is
how we're going to do it. Uh getting
together, discussing what needs to be
done and what's right for New New
Mexico. Um, I think, um, in the
beginning of all of this, because I
started back in 2015, um, uh, searching
for, um, groups out there that were
making an impact on New Mexico and, um,
trying to find, uh, people who were act,
um, doing this work. And it was so new
um that um I attended a lecture at UN M
uh for smoking sensation with um uh Dr.
um uh Matthew Johnson and it was very
eyeoping and I'm like going oh this is
this is what is this this is the future
this is what's going to happen to New
Mexico. So and then uh prior to that uh
Dr. Straman uh did DMT. So, New Mexico
uh as far as education and and training,
we have been doing it for um quite a
while. And that's not to um uh think
lightly of uh all the traditional heal
healers that have been doing this for
hundreds of years here. So uh you know
we have to integrate all of this and um
understand each other and talk about it
and uh start to come together and it
this isn't going to happen uh just
because a few people are doing it. It
it's going to happen with all of us
doing it all at the same time and uh
bring our views and our understanding
about uh this wonderful medicine that
has been shoved underground. And uh it
it doesn't need to be that way anymore.
We can start to study it and work with
it and start to heal people the way it
it's intended to be. So, um thank you
all for being here today. I know we have
uh a few more minutes left. Um, but I
know I up that time trying to come on to
the um uh to the call here, but um I
now's the time if anybody else wants to
speak up and um this would be uh an
appropriate time to do so.
>> Okay, not seeing anybody else raising
their hands or comments, Brenda. So with
that, just on behalf of the department,
thank you for chairing the meeting and
for doing this. Thank you to everybody
who uh was here and for your input. Um
we're really looking forward to it and
for the you know as far as for these
drafts moving forward. Um and uh and and
just as a little bit of a clarification.
So Brenda um because I was reminded of
this is the that deadline for the 15th
with regard to the draft is actually
whatever document that we have that
you've created and that we morph as it
goes through with the comments on the
meeting on the 6th. That's the document
that we're talking about as far as draft
and outline for the advisory board. So,
just wanted to clarify that in case
anybody who watched that meeting goes,
"Wait, but there was supposed to be
something." That's actually what's
there. Brenda did a great job in getting
it put together early. So, that gives us
a little extra time. Anyway, thank you
to everyone. And Brenda, back to you for
any final words.
>> Well, thank you everyone. Thank you, um,
Dominic again. And, um, I know there's,
uh, this is a small community of people.
uh New Mexico. Uh I don't know we what
we have two million people here in state
of New Mexico. Um it's amazing uh that
all of you have come out. Uh we are all
um showing our well we're not showing
our faces here but we're showing our
initials here and that shows me that um
how um thoughtful and caring um all of
you are to be a part of this and you all
are a part of this and I I thank you so
much for being here today and offering
up your knowledge, your experience, your
viewpoints uh to have this all come
together and and shape New Mexico for
the future. Thank you every one of you
and I'll see you all on March 16th at
1:00
sharp. Okay.
>> Thank you everybody.
>> Thank you.